A Guide to the Isaac Hammond Collection, 1839-1875
Library of Virginia
- Letter, 29 September 1864, Henry D. Flood, Lynchburg, [Virginia], to Governor William Smith concerning military exemptions., 2 p., ALS. (Folder 13)
- Letter, 3 October 1864, James A. Seddon, Secretary of War, C.S.A., Richmond, to William Smith, Governor of Virginia, stating that slaves are needed to work on fortifications around Richmond., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 14)
- Letter, 3 October 1864,J. F. Gilmer, Major General, Engineer Bureau, C.S.A., Richmond to J. A. Seddon, Secretary of War, Richmond, outlining a plan to requisition slaves to work on fortifications around Richmond., 2 p., daALS. (Folder 14)
- Extract, 5 October 1864, of Special Orders No. 71, Headquarters Post, Richmond, by command of Major General Kemper, by Garnett Andrews, A.A. General, releasing all slaves and free Negroes working on fortifications and being held in Castle Thunder on account of impressment will be released., 2 p., form filled in with endorsements. (Folder 14)
- Letter, 5 October 1864, B. I.[?] Johnson, Richmond, to Governor [William] Smith, asking that his slaves Robert and James be released from their impressment to work on fortification., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 14)
- Letter, 5 October 1865 Governor William Smith to Captain Richardson informing him that Smith is sending someone to oversee the discharge of all slaves and free Negroes unfit to work on fortifications., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 14)
- Letter, 5 October 1864, Governor William Smith to Colonel Smith asking for a list of all slaves and free Negroes being sent to work on fortifications at Drewery's Bluff., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 14)
- Notice, 5 October 1864, from Robert M. Taylor that his slave Creed has been impressed to work on fortifications., 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 14)
- Passes, 5 October 1864, issued to "Watson" by Captain William A. Charters, Provost Marshal's Office, Reserve Forces of Virignia, Richmond. Watson is to report to Miles George., 1 leaf, form filled in, two copies. (Folder 14)
- Note, 5 October 1864, from Thomas Hardgrove to unknown recepient regarding the arrest of his slave Randall., 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 14)
- Telegram, 6 October 1864, Captain C. T. Mason, Drewry's Bluff, to Governor William Smith asking Smith to send the next group of impressed laborers to Chaffin's Bluff., 1 leaf, form filled in. (Folder 14)
- Letter, 8 October 1864 P. W.[?] Loftbury[?], State Armory, Richmond, to Governor [William] Smith complaining that the production of ammunition at the Confederate States laboratory has stopped., 2 p., ALS. (Folder 14)
- Letter, 13 October 1864, George W. Munford, Secretary of Commonwealth, Richmond, to Clerk of County Court, Henrico County, [Virginia] sending a copy of An Act to Amend and Reenact an Act Further to Provide for the Public Defense. Munford's letter is attached to the copy of the act., 3 p., ALS. and printed material. (Folder 14)
- Letter, 21 October 1864, Colonel John C. Fiser, Savannah, Georgia, to S. Cooper, Adjutant and Inspector General, C.S.A., asking for a promotion to match his command., 2 p., ALS., including endorsements. (Folder 14)
- Extract, 29 October 1864, of Special Orders No. 317, Headquarters, Department of Richmond, by command of General Ewell, by T. O. Chestney, A. A. General, ordering Captain William English of the Governor's Mounted Guard to report to Governor William Smith., 1 leaf, printed form filled in. (Folder 14)
- Letter, 29 October 1864, Colonel J. B. Danforth, First Regiment, Virginia Reserves, Camp on New Bridge Road, to William Smith, Governor of Virginia, asking that Captain D. M. Lea's Cavalry be added to his command., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 14)
- Letter, 31 October 1864, James T. Johnson, Sycamore, [Pittsylvania County,] Virginia, to Governor [William] Smith concerning conscription., 8 p., ALS. (Folder 14)
- Letter, [probably 5 October] 1864, J. Redford to Lieutenant Gwathmey asking for the release of his slave Nelson., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 14)
- Absentee voter ballot, November 1864, with accompanying documents supplied by the state of New York, including envelopes, The Soldiers' Voting Bill of the State of New York: With Instructions from the Secretary of State,, and power of attorney., 2 envelopes, 1 leaf, and 8 p., printed material. (Folder 15)
- Letter, November 1864, Henry H. Davis, Point Lookout, Maryland, to James M. Baker. Davis, a prisoner of war, asks Baker to obtain some items for him., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 15)
- Report, 1 November 1864, of George Davis, Attorney General, C.S.A., to President Jefferson Davis, submitting the report of the Superintendent of Public Printing., 6 p., printed. (Folder 15)
- Letter, 2 November 1864, Samuel E. Dove to Governor [William Smith] concerning his exemption from military service as a druggist. Also contains an endorsement from the governor to Brigadier General Moore on 5 November 1864, and Moore's reply., 1 leaf and 2 p., ALS. (Folder 15)
- Memorial at a Meeting for Sufferings for North Carolina Yearly Metting of Friends, held at Deep River Meeting House in Guilford County, N.C., Eleventh month, 4th, 1864,, 4 November 1864, concerning Quakers suffering for refusal to perform military service., 1 leaf, printed. (Folder 15)
- Letter, 9 November 1864, President Jefferson Davis to William Smith, Governor of Virginia, acknowledging the receipt of a copy of resolutions passed at a meeting of governors., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 15)
- Letter, 16 November 1864, William B. Rodman, Petersburg, to W. T. Dortch concerning his personal and professional situations., 2 p., ALS. (Folder 15)
- Certificate, 18 November 1864, recommending extension of the furlough of Lieutenant D. E. Barker, Company C, 3rd Arkansas Regiment by the Examining Board, Danville, Virginia., 2 p., form filled in with endorsements. (Folder 15)
- Letter, 23 November 1864, unknown correspondent to Governor William Smith concerning conditions around Lynchburg, Virginia., 6 p., AMs. (Folder 15)
- Letter, 23 November 1864, John D. Williams, Fayetteville, to J. M. Baker, Richmond, concerning government finances., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 15)
- Letter, 26 November 1864, J. H. Myers, Savannah, [Georgia], to James M. Baker, Confederate States Senate, asking for an appointment as midshipman for his son., 3 p., ALS. (Folder 15)
- Letter, 28 November 1864, Lieutenant A. J. Coffer, Company E, 11th Florida Regiment, Howards Grove Hospital [Virginia], to A. R. Lawton, Brigadier General, Quartermaster General, C.S.A., asking permission to purchase material from the government in order to make a new uniform., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 15)
- Extract, 29 November 1864, of Special Orders No. 156, Headquarters, Reserve Forces of Virginia, Richmond, by command of Major General Kemper, by J. Mitchel, A.A.G., concerning J. P. Jones., 1 leaf, form filled in. (Folder 15)
- Letter, 29 November 1864,S. P. Moore, Surgeon General, Richmond, to William Smith, Governor of Virginia, regarding the distillation of fruits into liquor., 2 p., ALS. (Folder 15)
- Resolution, 30 November 1864, by the General Assembly of Florida regarding Captain J. J. Dickison, Company D, 2nd Florida Cavalry., 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 15)
- Statement, November 1864, in relation to the salaries of the officers of the Senate., 3 leaves, Ms. (Folder 15)
- Broadside, December 1864, standing committees of Senate of Virginia, extra session. No. 881[?] in More Confederate Imprints., 1 leaf, printed. (Folder 16)
- Message, 7 December 1864, of President Jefferson Davis to the Senate and House of Representatives submitting a communication from the Secretary of War regarding funds needed to meet a deficiency in the appropriation to pay the officers and employees of the War Department., 2 p., printed. (Folder 16)
- Report of the the Auditing Board of the State of Virginia, 9 December 1864, document no. XVII of the session of the Virginia General Assembly, 1864-1865. No. 873, document XVII in More Confederate Imprints., 6 p., printed. (Folder 16)
- Letter, 13 December 1864, J. W. Allan, in trenches near Bermuda Hundred, [Virginia], to "French" describing conditions in the front., 4 p., ALS. (Folder 16)
- Claim, 15 December 1864, of W. C. Sutton, Attala County, Mississippi, against the Confederate States of America, for slaves, horses, and mules captured., 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 16)
- Letter, 15 December 1864, Lieutenant A. Talbott, Headquarters, 4th Battalion, Local Defense, Chaffin's Farm, [Virginia], to Major T. O. Chestney, A.A.G., Department of Richmond, asking for a furlough., 2 p., ALS., with endorsements (Folder 16)
- Letter, 16 December 1864,L. H. Fitzhugh, Sergeant-at-Arms and Disbursing Officer, Confederate States Senate, to an unknown recipient sending a bill for advertising., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 16)
- Letter, 19 December 1864, Captain E. S. Gay, Public Guard, Richmond, to Governor [William] Smith informing Smith that Gay has ordered the leader of the band to report to Smith every music evening., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 16)
- Letter, 20 December 1864,G. A. Trenholm, Secretary of the Treasury, C.S.A., to William Smith, Governor of Virginia, concerning taxation on banks and railroads, including that part owned by a state., 2 leaves, ALS. (Folder 16)
- Report of the Commercial Agent of Virginai with the Accompanying Documents, 21 December 1864, document XIX of the Session of the Virginia General Assembly, 1864-1865. No. 2283 in Confederate Imprints., 12 p., printed (Folder 16)
- Letter, 27 December 1864, John J. Cohn to A. H. Stephens concerning Alice Moses and her husband., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 16)
- Letter, 27 December 1864,W. H. Richardson, Adjutant of Virginia, to [William Smith], Governor of Virginia returning to Smith a letter, 26 December 1864 from Lieutenant General R. S. Ewell to J. A. Seddon, Secretary of War, asking for reinforcements., 2 leaves, ALS. (Folder 16)
- Letter, 29 December 1864, Major General J. B. Gordon, 2nd Corps, Army of Northern Virginia, to Governor William Smith regarding a promotion for an officer., 4 p. ALS., includes endorsement. (Folder 16)
- Introductory Lecture Read before the Corps of Cadets, on the Resumption of the Academic Duties of the Virginia Military Institute, at the Alms House, Richmond, Virginia, December 28, 1864, by Francis H. Smith, A.M., Superintendent of the Va. Military Institute, 1865, published by Macfarlane & Fergusson, Printers. No. 4011 in Confederate Imprints., 8 p., printed. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 7 January 1865,J. L. Kemper, Major General, Headquarters, Reserve Forces of Virginia, to Governor [William] Smith concerning the Reserve Forces., 2 p., ALS. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 8 January 1865, Tazewell McCorkle to William Smith, Governor of Virginia, asking for a promotion to 2nd lieutenant for Company A, 1st Virginia Battalion., 2 p., ALS., with endorsements. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 9 January 1865, Captain A. Graham, Rockbridge Artillery, recommending Tazewell McCorkle for a promotion., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 16 January 1865, William F. Thompson, Richmond, to Governor [William] Smith asking for a promotion for his son Nortwin F. Thompson. Includes recommendations from Francis H. Smith; B. R. Johnson, Major General; J. L. Kemper, Major General; Thomas W. Gholson, A. T. Caperton, and R. M. T. Hunter., 3 p., ALS. (Folder 17)
- Montgomery Daily Mail, 31 January 1865, Montgomery Alabama. No. 5223 in Confederate Imprints, 2 p., printed
- Letter, February 1865, Mary Covington, Campbell County, [Virginia] to [Governor William Smith] regarding her destitute condition., 2 p., ALS. and wrapper. (Folder 17)
- Letter of commendation, 2 February 1865, for Private Edward R. Roxbury, Company H, 17th Virginia Infantry, by Colonel Arthur Herbert commanding 17th Virginia, and M. D. Corse, Brigadier General. Herbert's commendation was written December 1864 and Corse's 2 February 1865., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 17)
- Wrapper, 4 February 1865, for letter to Governor William Smith regarding an exemption for D. L. Crittenden of Fauquier County. Letter not included., 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 17)
- Message of the President, 6 February 1865,to the Senate and House of Representatives of the Confederate States of America submitting the report of the commissioners to confer with the President of the United States with a view to the restoration of peace. No. 637 in Confederate Imprints., 4 p., printed. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 9 February 1865, John B. A. Dimtry, Chief Clerk, Post Office Department, Richmond, to James M. Baker, Chairman of Senate Committee on Post Offices and Post Roads sending a copy of a letter, 8 April 1865, from John H. Reagan, Postmaster General, to Frank B. Sexton, Chairman of the House Committee of Post Offices and Post Roads, regarding the taking of postage stamps by the enemy., 1 leaf and 2 p., ALS. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 13 February 1865, Brigadier General Joseph R. Davis, Brigade Headquarters, to "Gentlemen" sending a resolution from his brigade concerning the use of African Americans as soldiers. Resolution not included., 2 p., ALS. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 14 February 1865,J. A. Campbell, Assistant Secretary of War, to A. T. Caperton, Confederate States Senate, acknowledging receipt of Caperton's letter regarding recruitment of foreigners., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 15 February 1865, Sarah Bryant, Bedford County, [Virginia], to Governor William Smith regarding her being destitute., 3 p., ALS., including wrapper. (Folder 17)
- Receipt, 16 February 1865, Southern Express Company issued to W. T. Dortch, Richmond, for money forwarded to Colonel William B. Rodman., 1 leaf, form filled in. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 20 February 1865, George C. Vanderslice, Batesville, Albemarle County, [Virginia], to R. M. T. Hunter, Richmond, asking about the peace conference Hunter attended., 3 p., ALS. (Folder 17)
- Circular letter, 21 February 1865, from soldiers in Pickett's Division who reside in Buckingham County, [Virginia], requesting that William M. Cabell allow them to use his name as a candidate for the House of Delegates. Includes Cabell's reply in the affirmative., 1 leaf, printed. (Folder 17)
- Extract, 21 February 1865, of Special Orders No. 43, Adjutant and Inspector General's Office, by command of the Secretary of War, by John Withers, Assistant Adjutant General, assigning Private Richard Buck to the Quartermaster's Department and to report to the quartermaster in Lake City, Florida., 1 leaf, form filled in. (Folder 17)
- Telegram, 21 February 1865, General P. G. T. Beauregard, Rock Hill, [South Carolina], to Colonel S. Bassett French referring French to the Quartermaster General., 1 leaf, form filled in. (Folder 17)
- Claims report, 22 February 1865, W. H. S. Taylor, Auditor, C.S.A., by T. Calvert, Chief Division, Deceased Soldiers, Treasury Department, C.S.A., Richmond, to A. H. Garland, Confederate States Senate, Richmond, concerning the claim of Rebecca Giles, widow of Oliver D. Giles of company A, 33rd Arkansas., 1 leaf, form filled in. (Folder 17)
- Telegram, 24 February 1865,W. H. Jackson, Brigadier General, Verona, [Mississippi], to I. G. Harris, Governor [of Tennessee] regarding his efforts for promotion., 1 leaf, form filled in. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 25 February 1865, an unknown Confederate soldier in the Army of Northern Virginia to Senator R. M. T. Hunter concerning the state of the army., 4 p., AMs. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 4 March 1865,R. S. Ewell, Lieutenant General, Headquarters, Department of Richmond, Richmond, to Governor William Smith regarding rasing a force to protect the city of Richmond in case of a sudden emergency., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 13 March 1865, F. L. Benson, Petersburg, to William Smith, Governor of Virginia, stating that he is an indigent soldier whose home, Portsmouth, is behind enemy lines, and asking if he and his family qualify for assistance., 2 p., ALS. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 17 March 1865, Governor William Smith to J. F. Slaughter regarding Slaughter's proposition on domestic manufactures., 2 p., ALS. (Folder 17)
- Wrapper, 17 March 1865, for letter to Governor William Smith concerning Camp Winder Hospital adn containing endorsement of Lieutenant General Richard Stoddert Ewell., 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 17)
- Daily Constitutional Whig, 24 March 1865, Augusta, Georgia. No. 5158 in Confederate Imprints., 4 p., printed.
- Letter, 4 May 1865, Henry Chiles, Richmond, to Captain Beckwith, United States Army, asking for permission to continue running his saloon., 2 leaves, ALS., one a copy. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 10 May 1865, Ellen O'Keeffe, Richmond, to General Patrick, Provost Marshall, United States Army, asking for permission to reopen her store., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 17)
- Richmond Whig, June 1865, Richmond, copy of message of Francis H. Pierpont, Governor of Virginia, to the general assembly meeting in extra session., 1 leaf, printed.
- Richmond Times, 15 August 1865, Richmond., 8 p., printed.
- Act, 1865, concerning free Negroes and slaves who may be organized as soldiers. In the Virginia General Assembly., 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 17)
- Resolution, 1865, authorizing the Sergeant-at-Arms to pay postage on letters and newspapers directed to members of the Senate. By James H. Nash, Secretary, [Confederate States] Senate., 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 17)
- Richmond Enquirer, 31 January 1875, Richmond., 4 p., printed.
- Act, n.d., for the compensation of female clerks and employees of the government by the Congress of the Confederate States., 2 leaves, Ms. (Folder 18)
- Broadside, n.d.,Slavery, by C. C. T., communicated for the Southern Friend., 1 leaf, printed. (Folder 18)
- Business card, n.d., of Charles A. Rose, attorney-at-law and notary public, Richmond, Virginia., 1 leaf, printed. (Folder 18)
- Business card, n.d., of the Maltby House, City Point, Virginia., 1 leaf, printed. (Folder 18)
- Circular letter, n.d., program at the Barnum Museum displaying an "original secessionist.", 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 18)
- axioms, n.d., compilation of miscellaneous axioms concerning the Civil War., 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 18)
- Bills, n.d., two $5, one $10, one $20, one $50, and one $100 Confederate notes., 12 p. (Folder 18)
- Letter, n.d., G. U.[?] Tr[?] to G. A. Henry inviting him to dinner., 1 leaf, ALS. (Folder 18)
- Letter, n.d., William Old, Jr., to an unknown recipient complaining about army officers, taxes, and other matters., 2 p., ALS., incomplete. (Folder 18)
- List, n.d., of ministers in Richmond, Virginia., 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 18)
- Joint resolution, n.d., of the Congress of the Confederate States of America regarding the claims of Zedekiah McDaniel of Kentucky and Francis M. Ewing of Mississippi., 1 leaf, Ms. (Folder 18)
- Summary, n.d., of Naval losses of the United States Navy and Confederate States Navy., 2 leaves, Ms. (Folder 18)
- Nonassigned bonds, n.d., authorized by the act of the Confederate Congress, 20 February 1863. Included are $100, $500, and $1,000 bonds., 3 items, printed.
- To the People of Georgia, n.d., from the Columbian., 1 leaf, 2 p., 1 original and 1 photocopy. (Folder 19)
- Visit from St. Nicholas by Clement C. Moore, n.d., from the Daily Union., 1 leaf, 2 p., 1 original and 1 photocopy. (Folder 19)
- Article, n.d., on difficulties in purchasing goods from farmers in southwestern Virginia and taxing them. From an unknown newspaper, 2 leaves, 2 p., 1 original and 2 photocopies. (Folder 19)
- Poems, n.d., from unidentified newspapers. The Flag of Our Union, I Love to Live, I Live to Love, Lines to a Lady, and Long Ago., 4 leaves, 1 original, 3 photocopies. (Folder 19)
- Carrier's Address to the Patrons of the Richmond Enquirer, 25 December 1859., 1 leaf, in fragments. (Folder 19)
- Treasury forms, n.d,. blank., 8 forms. (Folder 20)
- Form letter, n.d., asking to begin daily sessions of the Confederate House of Representatives with a prayer., 1 leaf, blank form. (Folder 21)
- Form letter, n.d., asking to begin daily sessions of the Confederate Senate with a prayer., 9 leaves, blank forms. (Folder 21)
- Forms, 1865, for listing payments for letters sent from Richmond, Virginia., 6 leaves, blank forms. (Folder 21)
- Passes, n.d., for the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad., 1 leaf, blank forms. (Folder 21)
- Passes, 1864, from the Provost Marshal of the Union army. Eleven passes are marked Pass to Baltimore, Md., the twelfth notes that the pass is good for return if only countersigned by the Provost Marshal in Washington, D.C., 12 leaves, blank forms. (Folder 21)
- Oaths of Allegiance, n.d., to the United States., 3 leaves, blank forms. (Folder 21)
- Form letter, 1865, ordering officers to forward descriptive lists and pay and clothing accounts of men in the U.S. General Hospital at Fortress Monroe, Virginia., 13 leaves, blank forms. (Folder 21)
- Form, n.d., from Office of the Confederate States Senate certifying payment for services to the Senate., 3 leaves, blank forms. (Folder 21)
- Requisition form, n.d., for the Confederate States Senate., 1 leaf, blank form. (Folder 21)
- Drafts, n.d., on the Treasure of the Confederate States., 2 leaves, blank forms. (Folder 21)
- Passes, 1865, for enlisted men in the Union army to pass within Richmond city limits at all hours., 3 leaves, blank forms. (Folder 21)
- Checks, n.d., on the Treasurer of the Confederate States., 3 leaves, blank forms (2 white, 1 blue). (Folder 21)
- Certification, n.d., for documents of the Confederate States., 2 leaves, blank forms. (Folder 21)
- Transportation invoices, 1864, for the Confederate States of America., 3 leaves, blank forms. (Folder 21)
- Card, 1865, for rent of box at the Richmond post office., 1 leaf, blank form. (Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous items, n.d., being presentation cards and scraps of letters., 10 leaves and 2 p. (Folder 21)
- Letterhead, n.d., from State of Virginia, Executive Department, Richmond., 2 blank sheets. (Folder 21)
- Blank sheet of paper. (Folder 21)
- Photograph, n.d., of Captain John Tayloe of King George County, [Virginia]., 1 photograph and 1 photocopy. (Folder 22)
- Print, [ca. 1862], of Union Generals., 1 leaf. (Folder 22)
- Print, n.d.,Attack on the Massachusetts 6th at Baltimore, April 19th, 1861., 1 leaf. (Folder 22)
- Print, n.d.,Napoleon I. Meditating on the Eve of the Battle of Austerlitz., 1 leaf. (Folder 22)
- Print, n.d., frontspiece from a Forget Me Not Album., 1 leaf. (Folder 22)
- Envelope, n.d., addressed to Mr. Nash, Secretary of the Senate from the Confederate War Department., 1 envelope. (Folder 23)
- Envelope, n.d., addressed to Hon. James M. Baker, C. S. Senate, Richmond, Virginia, from Executive Department, Tallahassee, Florida., 1 envelope. (Folder 23)
- Envelope, n.d., addressed to Hon. James M. Baker, Chairman of Senate Committee on Post-offices and Post-roads from Confederate Postmaster General., 1 envelope. (Folder 23)
- Envelope, n.d., addressed to the Military Commanders at Lexington and other points in Kentucky from the Confederate Navy, Office of Ordnance and Hydrography., 1 envelope. (Folder 23)
- Envelope, n.d., addressed to Hon. Allen T. Caperton, C. S. Senate from Confederate Department of State., 1 envelope. (Folder 23)
- Envelope, n.d., addressed to Hon. Messrs. Walker and Jaimeson [Jemison], C. S. Senate, Richmond, from Confederate Adjutant and Inspector General's Office., 1 envelope. (Folder 23)
- Envelope, n.d., from Executive Department, Virginia, no address., 1 envelope. (Folder 23)
- Confederate blank stationary. (Folder 24)